<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Morbus epidemicus, or The churles sickenesse In a sermon preached before the iudges of the assises. By T.P.</title>
            <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849809</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09510)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1181:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Morbus epidemicus, or The churles sickenesse In a sermon preached before the iudges of the assises. By T.P.</title>
                  <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Thomas Creede for Arthur Iohnson, and are to bee solde at his shoppe in Paules Churchyard, at the White Horse, neere the great north dore of Powles,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Pestell.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The churles sicknesse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORBVS EPIDEMICVS, OR THE CHVRLES <hi>SICKENESSE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preached before the Iudges <hi>of the Aſſiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY T. P.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. TIM. 6.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The deſire of money is the roote of all euill, which while ſome luſted after, they erred from the faith, and pierced themſelues through with many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Thomas Creede</hi> for <hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> and are to bee ſolde at his ſhoppe in <hi>Paules</hi> Churchyard, at the White Horſe, neere the great North dore of
<hi>Powles.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:2"/>
            <head>TO MY NOBLE AND worthy Patrone, Sir <hi>Thomas Beamont</hi> Knight, of <hi>Coleorton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Sir, I ſhall need (I hope) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther long-winded Periods, nor circklings and trauerſings to diſcouer, how much I am in duty for euer engaged to you: ſince it's apparant enough that my whole maintenance hitherto hath beene from you alone, nor thereby to draw you to thinke that I meane as I ſpeake: which I am already fullie perſwaded you doe. Let it ſuffice then, that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, there was no other motiue or inducement of publiſhing this Sermon, but onely a deſire the world ſhould take notice, that if I could doe any thing, it ſhould bee to you principally directed. God knowes I am farre from thinking any thing in this worth a good thought, it being a thing faſhioned and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the extremity of my ſickeneſſe (and ſo will ſeeme I know to all of ſound iudgement) and in the minority and infancy of my ſtudies in Diuinity: yet it is by iuſt title yours, whoſe I was then, and am <pb facs="tcp:14978:3"/>ſtill, and for Whoſe ſeruice it was then deliuered. And I truſt you are able to quitte me from any peece of pride or oſtentation in this matter: So that all my ambition in this publication is (next Gods glory) to pleaſe you, who perchance in not aſſenting to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, do many times affoord mee the commendation, whereof I confeſſe my ſelfe altogether vnworthy, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it deſerue any prayſe, that I am, and euer will be a faithfull honourer of you, and your Noble Lady, beſeeching the higheſt not to take his bleſſings from you, nor from your children after you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS PESTELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14978:3"/>
            <head>MORBVS EPIDEMICVS, <hi>OR</hi> The Churles Sicknes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLESIASTES 5.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There is an euill ſickeneſſe I haue ſeene vnder the Sunne.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Reuerend opinion (Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, Right Worſhipfull, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) is exacted fiem vs in regard of the Author of theſe words. T'is a King that ſpeakes, a wiſe, apreaching King, King <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the Preacher. Nay, loe! a greater, a wiſer then <hi>Solomon</hi> is here: He was a wiſe King; the wiſeſt; had a wiſe Spirit giuen him of God. Here's the King, the ſpirit the God of wiſdome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Solomon</hi> onely, the Penne-man, who winged with this heauenly ſpirite, did ouerſoare and eſcape the vaine things which are done vnder the Sun: One of which hee here entreates of, and call's it
<hi>Nalum Infirmum,</hi> a ſicke ilneſſe, or an euil ſicknes.
<hi>There's an euill ſicknes I haue ſeene vnder the Sunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text hath two parts: Firſt, an Aſſertion, <hi>There's an euill ſickneſſe.</hi> Secondly, a Probation, or <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14978:4"/>euidence, and that's double: Firſt, I haue ſeen't (ſaies
<hi>Solomon</hi>) Secondly, the place where. <hi>Vnder the Sunne.</hi> The Aſſertion is a Deſcription of Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, It's an euill; it's a ſickneſſe, and ti's an euill ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>Couetouſneſſe (ſayeth <hi>Auſtine</hi>) is in all things, in euery deſire, as of honour, knowledge, &amp;c. and ſo is term'd the root of all euill: but more ſtrictly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, t'is defin'd by the three cauſes: Firſt, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, an immoderate deſire; 2. the material riches; 3. the efficient, a diffidency or diſtruſt in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence. Which vice (ſayes the Philoſopher) conſiſts eſpecially in three things. 1. An ouer-earneſt, and couetous deſire of getting. 2. A griping and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carefull keeping. 3. baſeneſſe and beaſtlineſſe in diſpenſing. Now though <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeake principally of one, or mixtly of two of theſe; namely, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Now though <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeake principally of one, or mixtly of two of theſe; namely, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and torturing of the couetous ſoule, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no ioy in the enioying of his wealth, no quiet or contentment, but on the contrary is hurt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammaged. For ſo it followes in the verſe. <hi>I haue ſeene an euill ſickneſſe,</hi> to witte, <hi>Riches reſerued to the owners thereof, for their euill.</hi> Yet ſince hee ſpeakes in the 15. verſe, againſt this vaine deſire in generall, and calles it there by the ſame name, <hi>Anouill ſicknes:</hi> Therefore I purpoſe to diſcourſe of the wordes, as a generall deſcription of this ſinne. And indeed I may diſcourſe and handle it at my pleaſure, but to ſmall purpoſe. For what ſhould this aſſemblie heare of couetouſneſſe? Is this a fitte Text for the Aſſiſes? I might haue kept this Sermon for the Citie, among Tradeſmen and Vſurers: But I will reſt a while, and ſhew you the fitneſſe of ſuch a Theme for this time, place, and perſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I muſt intreat you to vnderſtand and remember (Right Honourable and Chriſtian au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) that Couetouſneſſe, as it is an immoderate <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14978:4"/>deſire of riches, in the interior affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſoule; ſo it's oppoſed to liberality; but as it imports an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant and vnmeet acception, and keeping vp of money: ſo ti's contrary to Iuſtice, and in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde not vnfitte for the time. Againe, becauſe this ſinne is a ſuperfluous loue of hauing riches; it exceedes in two things. Firſt, t'is exceſſiue in retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and on this part ariſes hence an obduration and hardneſſe of heart againſt mercy, when a man turns clemency into vengeance, and is not relieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the poore: Secondly, it exceedes in taking, and ſo it fals two wayes into conſideration; eyther as it is in the affection, and ſo thence ariſes anguiſh, and diſquietneſſe, ſuperfluous cares and buſie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction. 2. or as it is in the effect: and thus whiles it couets other mens goods: it vſes ſomtimes force, which belongs to violence; and ſometimes craft, which craft if it bee committed in any buſineſſe, then as it reſpects the things themſelues, it is deceipt, but as it concernes the perſons, t'is betraying as in <hi>Iudas.</hi> But be the craft vſed in word onely, then t'is cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage in a ſimple and bare word: and if an oath bee added, periuty. And all theſe (ſaies <hi>Gregorie</hi>) are the ſpawne and brood of Couetouſnes.</p>
            <p>Now wee all know, that theſe vermine, this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Vipers, will bee very buſie at euerie Aſſiſes, violence and oppreſsion, crafty deceipt, and couſonage, betraying &amp; periury. Which being true, I feare me, the curſed damme will likewiſe finde a roome amongſt vs. Eſpecially, if wee call to minde, that <hi>Encomion</hi> of
<hi>Baſil</hi> concerning this ſinne, which is (ſayes he) the mother and miſtreſſe of all ſinne and miſchiefe, which commits ſacriledge, theft and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine; makes warres and ſlaughters, ſels and buyes by
<hi>Simony:</hi> askes and receiues wickedly, does com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce and take vſury vniuflly; dealing falſly by craft and couſenage; diſſolues couenants, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14978:5"/>lates oaths, corrupts teſtimonies, &amp; peruerts iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And to come to examine the preſent times. Whats now the reaſon, that almoſt halfe the worlde is turn de Incloſers, Vſurers or Banqueroutes, that the common Gaoles haue more poore debtors, then deſperate fellons? Whats the fountaine of ſo many ſuites and law-caſes, but onely this eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll? Men are ſicke of Couetouſneſſe. <hi>Achah</hi> would haue <hi>Naboths</hi> vine-yard. What makes ſo many periuries and falſe accuſations, but Couetouſneſſe? In any wrong done to our ſoule or body, by wounds, by diſgrace, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy; wee can many times put vp, and be quiet, but the leaſt priuate endamagement is enough to ſet vs together by the eares. It our wealth bee impayred but the value of nine pence, oh then our Free-hold is touched: it will beare an action, let him looke to it. If once <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> (ſayeth one) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wrangle for priuate profite, bee on foote, then we preſently buſtle, wee ride, runne, crouch, kneele, vſe the cappe, the barre, the tongue, the ſworde. Then the young ſonne enquires of his olde fathers yeares, and ſendes out <hi>Form-dons</hi> after his death, quarrels with his mothers Ioynture, threatens his brothers with an entayle, and vpon queſtion of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets abridges his ſiſters portions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſo ſittes the time, that if with old <hi>Latimer</hi> I ſhould cry nothing but Beware of couetouſneſſe, Beware of Couetouſneſſe, it would (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture) proue a ſufficient preſeruatiue againſt this poyſon, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals:
<hi>radicent,</hi> the roote of all euill: and <hi>Solomon</hi> heere, an euill ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt part of which Text is (as I tolde you) a deſcription of Couetouſneſſe; and the firſt part of the Deſcription is, It's an Euil I.</p>
            <p>Euill properly taken (ſayeth the Schoole) and by it ſelfe, is not any thing created or exiſting, but <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14978:5"/>ſignifies a meere abſence of that good which ſhould be preſent, and is oppoſed to good priuatiuely, not poſitiuely; and as in Philoſophy t'is double, Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Morall: So in Diuinity there is <hi>Malum Culpae,</hi> and <hi>Malum Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> an euill, which is ſinne, &amp; an euill which is a puniſhment for ſinne. And in both theſe kinds wee ſhall finde this ſinne to bee an euill. Firſt, it's an euill of ſinne; a ſinnefull euill, an euill full of ſinne: nothing more ſinnefull. <hi>Anaro nihil ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestius, nihil iniquius quam amare pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiam,</hi> Ecclus. 2. T'is the roote, the element, the Metropolis of all ſinnes. All other, as Bribery, Simonie, Vſary, Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Deceit, lyes, Oathes are (ſayeth one) Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for this, and ſerue as Porters to fetch and bring her liuing in. A ſinne firſt againſt God, therefore for bidden to the chiefe men, <hi>Leuit.</hi>
17.17. For the couetous man deſpiſes him: Hee bleſſeth himſelfe, and contemneth the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3. He makes golde his hope, and the wedge of golde his conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. T'is flat and plaine Idolatry,
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring his coyne before God, as the Gadarenes did their ſwine before Chriſt: For he holdes it his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, thinking himſelfe made and vndone by it, and his Redeemer and preſeruer from depth and danger, and differs from the Idalat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r in this, that where hee hath but one Image, the couetous man hath many Maumets.</p>
            <p>A ſinne ſecondly, againſt our neighbours, <hi>Venenum charitatis</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Auſtirte</hi>) the poyſon of charity, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iniury to ſo many as hee is able to relieue: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king men murderers, lyers and theeues: Marderers: They lay wayte for bloud, and lye priuily for their liues; ſuch are the wayes of euery one that's greedie of gaine, <hi>Prouerb.</hi>
1.18. And in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 32.6. The nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard will ſpeake of niggardneſſe, and his heart wil worke iniquity, to doe wickedly, and ſpeake falſly againſt the Lord, (there hee is a lyar) to make empty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14978:6"/>the hungry ſoule, and cauſe the drinke of the thirſtie to fayle: there he is a theefe.</p>
            <p>A ſinne euen againſt common honeſty, againſt friendſhip, ſeuering very brethren: Luk. 13. A ſin which as it makes a man monſtrous, with ſuch an heart as no man hath, without a bottome: ſo it is monſtrous in it ſelfe, vnnaturall, infinite. <hi>Monſtrum horrendum ingens, cui lumen ademptum;</hi> wanting the light of reaſon, and naturall vnderſtanding, which ſinne if it may admit compariſon with any naturall things; they muſt bee eyther the two outragious elements (for ſo t'is violent as fire, ſeeding on the ſubiected matter, and at once embracing another; &amp; furious as water, bearing downe all before it like a torrent, or a water-wracke) or elſe it may be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the deuouring Harpyes, and birds of prey, that are cruell to all, and therefore affect and ſelect ſolitarie and vnfrequented places.</p>
            <p>I aſt of all it is an euill that makes a man euerie beaſts fellow, nay, the worſt beaſts companion: for hee is an horſe-leach (ſayeth <hi>Solomon</hi>) crying, ſtill giue giue; a Moldewarpe, blacke by his wickednes, blind in his ignorance, and ſo many poſſeſſions, ſo many Mole-hils, in which he buries himſelfe by perpetuall anguiſhing and torturing his owne ſoule. Like an Hogge (ſayeth <hi>Prudentius</hi>) euer rooting, neuer doing good till hee die: and as the Hogge ſends one Acorne downe his ſtomacke, chewes an other, and greedily ſnatcheth at a third: ſo this Hogge-mans hunger is inſatiable. Like a Dogge (ſayeth
<hi>Seneca</hi>) that what euer is caſt vnto him, choppes it in whole, and ſtands gaping for the next.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee it is <hi>Malum culpae,</hi> and euill of ſinne, a ſinne impious, vncharitable, diſhoneſt, bloodie, the euiſh, lying an vnnaturall, monſtrous and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euill. And not onely thus is it an euill of ſinne, but <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14978:6"/>it is alſo <hi>Malum poenae,</hi> an euill puniſhment for ſinne: <hi>In ſeſe armatus furor:</hi> for it is a ſinne againſt a mans ſelfe, his owne ſoule and body. His ſoule, ſo ſayeth <hi>Auſtin, Amor terrenorum, viſcus ſpiritualium pennarum:</hi> The exceſsiue loue of earthly things is the birdlime of a mans ſpirituall feathers, lyming and entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling both the ſoules wings, her vnderſtanding, and her will; and is therefore noted to bee a ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,
<hi>Mark.</hi> 7.23. comming from within, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing a man, alwayes breeding and begetting a ſwarme and <hi>Hydra,</hi> &amp; wheele of cares in his boſome; dulling his very heart, and making it like <hi>Nabals,</hi> hard and heauy as a ſtone.</p>
            <p>Againſt his body: For the couetous wretch is carefull to riſe earely in the morning, to goe late to bed, eating the bread of penſiue carefulneſſe: hee tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s vp and downe to the market, turnes ouer his Kalender, <hi>Fit ex Domino Procurator,</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Sencca</hi>) of a Lord and Maſter, hee becomes a baſe ſeruant or a drudge; baſe and ſordide in his apparrell, vſing himſelfe to meates, not onely vile, and of no price; but euen hard and horrible to bee lookt vpon: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding, couſening his owne <hi>Genius</hi> both of food and reſt. <hi>Surely, to a man that is good in his ſight, God giues wiſdome and knowledge, and ioy: but to the ſinner he giues paine togather and heape vp,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. vlt. So that hee gathers riches, as the Phoenix doth drie ſtickes to burne her ſelfe. Hee is a meere poſſeſſor of wealth: for his couetous heart keepes the Key of it, and lockes it from his comfortable vſe: He ſits by his money, as a ſicke man by his meate, &amp; hath no power to take it: He couets to couet, labours to labour; as an Aſſe, which all day carries trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and is much galled and bruiſed with his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but enioyes no comfort in his carriage: And therefore <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> compares a couetous man, to a man poſſeſt with a Deuill, who is vext and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14978:7"/>in his body. So that, if a man will haue but ſo much care as <hi>Peter</hi> wiſhed Chriſt to haue, to be good to himſelfe: it will bee cauſe inough to draw him from this curſed euill, which is not onely an euill of ſinne, but an euill puniſhment for ſinne.</p>
            <p>But becauſe many euill and couetous world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eſteeme themſelues notwithſtanding all this euill, to bee yet in good eſtate, and in health; it now followes, that wee proue it to bee a ſickneſſe, and all ſuch men in danger of their ſoules health: <hi>There's an euill ſicknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The couetous man imagines himſelfe a poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, but himſelfe indeed is poſſeſt; and wee may as truely ſay, this ſickneſſe hath the man, as this man the ſickneſſe. A diſeaſe then it is euen by <hi>Tullies</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion: <hi>Illi morbo qui permanat in venas, &amp; inharet in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceribus, nec erelit poteſt. nomen eſt Auaritia, quae it a mentes hominum aſirictas tenet, vt cas nullo modo reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare permittat:</hi> That diſeaſe (ſayeth hee) which ſinks into the veines and bowels, and cannot be drawne thence, giuing a man no time of breathing, is coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: So that it ſeemes to bee no acute ſicknes, (as Phyſitians ſpeakes) for foureteene dayes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Chronicall diſeaſe for longer continuance, and where all other diſeaſes haue commonly foure parts; this hath but two: a beginning and an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; but neyther State, nor Diminution, and therefore in this there is no place left for a <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to bee expected. Now as all weakenes and diſeaſes of the body, are from ſome wickedneſſe, eyther from ſome defect in our conception, or diſorder in our conuerſation; ſo this laſt giues being and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to this of the ſoule; for it riſes vpon a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletion, a ſuefet, an ouercharging; not cauſed by the intemperature of the Heauens, or any externall violence. A repletion not of digeſtible food, but as if
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14978:7"/>if a man ſhould eate ſtickes and ſtones, and fire, and brimſtone; no maruell if they make him ſicke: nay it is a dangerous ſickneſſe, a ſickeneſſe vnto death: and if a man bee taken with it, wee may iuſtly ſeare his life; for wee are taught, that he which hates co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, his dayes ſhall bee prolonged vpon earth,
<hi>Prou.</hi> 28.16. And this ſinne it hath all the ſigns and ſymptomes of a diſeaſe; Firſt, vomiting. Hee hath deuoured ſubſtance, and ſhall vomit it, for God ſhall (bee his Phyſitian, and purge him, and ſhall) draw it out of his belly, <hi>Iob.</hi> 20.15. Secondly, want of ſleepe and reſt: <hi>All his dayes are ſorrowe, and his trauell is grieſe, his heart alſo takes no reſt in the night.</hi> Eccleſ. 2.23. Whoſe eſtate is therefore more baſe, (ſayeth <hi>Olimpiodoras</hi>) then the moſt wretched ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; for the couetous mans money which is his Maſter, will not allow him ſleepe. Hee cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed poſſibly take any reſt, but is euer tumbling &amp; toſſing, as King <hi>Achab,</hi> when deſire of <hi>Naboths</hi> vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard had once pierced and poſſeſt his ſoule, the Text ſayeth, Hee came home heauy and euill apai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, throwes himſelfe vpon his bed, and there hee languiſheth, and winds himſelfe, turnes away his face, and would eate no bread; for he was maw-ſick, ſtomacke-ſicke of couet ouſnes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſhew apparantly. that couetouſnes is a diſeaſe, be the dreames of the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>men, who are ſicke of it:
<hi>As the hungry man dreames, and be hold hee eateth, and when hee awakes, his ſoule is empty; or as a thirſty man dreawes, and loe, he is drinking, and when hee awakes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold hee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faint, and his ſoule longs.</hi> Iſaiah, 29.8. So (ſayeth
<hi>David</hi>) When theſe men haue ſlept their ſleepe, and haue awaked, they haue found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing in their honds: And as ſicke men are
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by troubled with fant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſticall and terrible dreams
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no queſtion but theſe mens dreames ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> horror and affrightment, ſtill thinking o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14978:8"/>and robbers, that came to deſpoyle them of their goods, their gods of ſiluer and golde: or if theyr dreames, like alluſions of the Deuill ſeeme merrie; yet they are ſadde and ſorrowfull in the euent and interpretation. The rich man in the Goſpell ſpeaks betwixt ſleeping and waking; <hi>Soule take thy eaſe, Thou hast goods layde vp inſtore for thee, for many yeeres.</hi> This was his dreame, and it was a very fine one, and a merry; but when Chriſt comes to expound it, you know what hee ſayeth: <hi>Thou foole, this night wil they fetch thy ſoule from thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe thinge bee that thou haſt gathered together,</hi> Luk 12.20.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue heard it proued an euill, and a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: Now put them both together, and you ſhal find it an euill ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>For firſt, it is a Leproſie, a ſpirituall Leproſie, though it turnde to a reall and a corporall Leproſie in <hi>Gehezi;</hi> who by Couetouſneſſe became a Leaper as white as ſnow, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.
<hi>vlt.</hi> And as in the Leper, there is an vniuerſall deprauation and corruption of all the humours; and a generall infection of all his members: ſo in this ſicknes all the humours; that is, all the good affections of his ſoule are corrupt; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the <hi>Humidum radicale,</hi> the moyſture of his roote and heart; his Charity, that is conſumed and dryed away. Nay, in all the powers and ſaculties both of ſoule and body, hee is altogether corrupt, &amp; become abhominable.</p>
            <p>Againe it is an euill ſicknes: for it is a perpetuall inward waſting and <hi>Dyſentery:</hi> and therefore the phraſe in
<hi>Iude,</hi> is, that ſuch men are powred out, or caſt away by the deceit of <hi>Balaam;</hi> wages: ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is this euill, ſo raging is this ſickenes, that it makes men diſſolute and caſt-awayes: It is an euill ſickenes.</p>
            <p>It is the <hi>Spleene:</hi> for as that increaſing; all other naturall partes decreaſe; ſo the encreaſe of Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14978:8"/>is the downefall and decay of all Chriſtian vertues, Liberality, Iuſtice, Charity, &amp;c. Which ſwelling couetous Spleene ſo growes vpon a man, that it hardens it ſelfe againſt all ſoft and ſupple me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. All their gentle pilles will not moue him, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l hee come at length to a conſumption; that hee may ſay with <hi>Dauid, My dayes are like a ſhadow, and I am withered like graſſe.</hi> Pſal. 102.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An euill ſickenes;</hi> for its a Lethargie; a dull and ſleepy diſeaſe, cauſing a man to take no true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in heauen and heauenly things; but ſetting and ſetling, and rooting his affections on the earth, neuer enioying one dramme or ſcruple of contentment, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes drooping and heauy. For the Diuell hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him ſuch a drouſie Opiate, that all their <hi>Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Exhilarans</hi> cannot rouſe him from his Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, nor their <hi>Latificans Galem</hi> ſhake him from his dumpes, and make him merry.</p>
            <p>It is yet worſe, to witte, the <hi>Greedy-worme.</hi> For the heart ſet on fire with couetouſneſſe, cannot bee ſatisfied or quenched with boughes and wood of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but onely with the earth of the graue. This is Gods puniſhment (ſayeth one) on the couetous heart, that neyther with enough, nor with too much bee ſhould bee contented. T'is in truth more then the Greedy-worme, t'is the Wolfe, ſtill eating, &amp; yet ſtill keeping the body leane: T'is paſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and is come to <hi>Caninus Appetitus,</hi> an l hungrie, a dogged diſeaſe, catching at others: nay, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinus</hi> a Woluiſh diſpoſition, euen diſpatching them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An euill ſicknes:</hi> for it is a burning Feuer, and as in that, ſo in this are commonly gnawing of the ſtomacke, intollerable thirſt, watchings, and many times rauings. A burning Feuer: for ſo (ſayeth <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>) The inſatiable loue of riches, doth farre more heat and torture men, then their vſe doth coole &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14978:9"/>them. <hi>Saeuior ignibus Actnae, ardens amor ſcruet habendi</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Boetius</hi>): A right Ague: for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man hath three ſeuerall ſits (ſayeth <hi>Gregory</hi>) for while hee liues here, he burnes twice, in the hote concupiſcence, and in the manifold care of getting and keeping his wealth; <hi>Et poſt modum ardebit in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a;</hi> and ſhall burne afterwards in hell fire: there is like to be his foreſt fitte, when he ſhall haue both an hote and a colde fitte, when hee ſhall both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely burne till he cry againe. <hi>There ſhall be wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> ſayeth our Sauiour, when hee ſhall bee colde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely: for <hi>There ſhall bee gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> And of this Feuer let him neuer hope for recouery; It will then turne to a perfect Quotidian Ague for euery day, nay for euer, and a day. <hi>An euill ſicknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is indeed a madneſſe, which commonly brings with it Debility and weakenes of the heade, watchings, thoughts, fancies, rauenous appetite, &amp; hollow eyes: And as mad men are wont to conceiue ſtrange things of themſelues, that they bee Kings or great men: ſo thoſe which are tainted with this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, doe imagine many goodly matters; making their riches a ſtrong City, and an high wall in their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination (ſaveth
<hi>Solomon</hi>) Prou. 18.11.</p>
            <p>An euill ſicknes, nay worſe then vſually euill; T'is the plague: And therefore as the ghoſt of <hi>Hector,</hi> in the fire of
<hi>Troy,</hi> cryed out to <hi>Aeneas: Heu fuge Nate Ded, teque his eripe ſtammis,</hi> Flie thou ſonne of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe from amidſt theſe flames. So the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> hauing called the deſire of money, the roote of all euill, addes in the next place: <hi>But ò thou man of God flie theſe things, Fuge Nate Deo,</hi> Thou childe of God, ſhe theſe things; flie from this miſchieuous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, as from an infection: <hi>Per mare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> per ſaxa,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour giuing warning to ſhun this plague ſayeth, <hi>Take heede of it Take heede of it, as an euill: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it as a ſicknes: Take heed and beware of it at an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14978:9"/>ſickneſſe. Take heede and beware of Couetouſnes,</hi> Luk. 13.1. And we ſhall finde that this plaguy couetous mans company and breath are infectious, to eate and drinke with him dangerous: Eate thou not the bread of him that hath an euill eye, neyther deſire thou his dainty meare: for as though hee thought in his heart, ſo hee will ſay vnto thee, Eate and drinke, but his heart is not with thee: Thou ſhalt vomite the morſels thou haſt eaten, &amp;c. <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.6.7.8. And to conclude, as men infected with the plague, are kept vp by others: ſo theſe men do keepe and hurdle vp themſelues, hauing indeed the marks and tokens of Gods wrath in then fleſh to be ſeene (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayeth) Your golde and ſiluer is ruſty, and the ruſt thereof ſhall bee a witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you: It ſhall feed vpon your fleſh like fire.) And to whom wee may well ſay, as to men in that caſe: <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, it is worthily intituled an <hi>Euill ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi> becauſe it is a ſicknes and diſeaſe incurable. So the Philoſopher in his <hi>Ethicks</hi> cals it <hi>Malum inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabile:</hi> and therefore is it incurable, becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe men being ſicke, are notwithſtanding vnwilling to bee eaſed, when that's the firſt part of health (ſayeth <hi>Sencca</hi>)
<hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lle ſanari:</hi> to wiſh for cure. And Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Ipſe ſibi denegat curam, qui ſuam Medico non pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licat cauſam:</hi> Which the couetous man will not. He cannot abide any wholeſome preſcriptions, and vnleſſe you will miniſter vnto him <hi>Vnguentum aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>Electuarium de Gemmis,</hi> hee will none of your Phyſicke: Wee may ſee it exemplified. The young man in the Goſpell, who (as with a Tympanie) was ſwollen and growne bigge with great poſſeſſions: Our Sauiour would haue purged him throughly: <hi>Goe and ſell all:</hi> but he would none. Such a plague is this euill, ſuch a madneſſe, ſuch a burning Feuer, ſuch a Greedyworm, ſuch a Lethargy, ſuch a Spleen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14978:10"/>Conſumption, and ſo contagious a Leproſie, that there is no meanes to redreſſe or remedy the ſame, vnleſſe theſe ſicke Lepers (like him in the Goſpell) will fall downe at the feet of Chriſt Ieſus, and cry vnto him: <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make mee cleane and whole:</hi> for with man (ſayeth Chriſt) it is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt part of the Text, the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>There's an euill ſickneſſe.</hi> The firſt part of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence followes, which is, <hi>I haue ſeene it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſe King dooth heere report that hee had ſeene it: wee may thence deriue this point of doctrine, that for a man to bee couetous is an high point of foolerie: for ſo hee ſeemes to infer. <hi>I haue ſeene it,</hi> and but ſeene it, ſeene it in others, not knowne it in my ſelfe: ſo that the onely ſeeing, and no more, proues
<hi>Solomon</hi> wiſe, but more then ſeeing, ſeeking, and hoarding vp of wealth, argues men fooles and ſots. I, you may call them at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but you cannot proue them ſo. No, Why? what greater ſign of a foole, then to do a thing for no cauſe, and to no end. <hi>The foole</hi> (ſayeth
<hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer in his owne conceit then ſeuen men that can render a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> So that rendering a reaſon is put for a point of wiſdome, which in this point, the couetous man can no point performe. For ſo ſayeth <hi>Dauid,</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, man walkes as a ſhade, and diſquiets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in vaine, heaping vp riches, and cannot tel who ſhall gather them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. <hi>There is no end of his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, neyther thinks hee for whom doe I trauell, and defraud my ſelfe of pleaſure. Eccleſ.</hi> 4.8. They labour for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: for <hi>the winde,</hi> as it is afterwards in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They conceiue chaffe, and bring forth ſtubble: <hi>Iſay.</hi> 33.11. Hauing no end in their deſire, no end for their deſire, no finall cauſe: Onely couetous to hide it, as
<hi>Achan</hi> confeſſed in <hi>Ioſua:</hi> 7.21. I ſaw among the ſpoyles a goodly Babyloniſh garment, and two <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14978:10"/>hundred ſhekels of ſiluer, and a wedge of gold of fifty ſhekels weight, and I coueted them, and tooke them, and loe! they lie hid in the midſt of my tent. Was not this (thinke you) a goodly wiſdome? Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not an Ape or a Iacke-daw doe as much? Againe, is it not an high point of baſe foolery for a man to ſit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his earthly traſh, like an henne or a brood-gooſe; and in the meane time to neglect the inward and and ſpirituall riches of the ſoule? as though a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man or great Perſonage ſhould trifle out his time in buying pinnes; pinnes? Nay worſe, plaine Mucke (ſayeth the Scripture) and dung: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle cals it <hi>Filthy Lucre,</hi> becauſe alway ſome dirt cleaues vnto it. Tirus <hi>did build her a ſtrong holde, and heaped vp ſiluer as the duſt, and gold as the mire in the ſtreetes.</hi> Zachar. 9.3. <hi>Shall not all theſe take vp a Parable, and a taunting Prouerbe against him, and ſay, Hoe! Hee that encreaſeth that which is not his: and hee that lades himſelfe with thicke Clay.</hi> Habac. 2.6.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, would any but a foole forget hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, his true, his new Manſion: and fall to building, in his Inne, to thinke of furniſhing and hanging it with <hi>Arras,</hi> where he is ſure hee cannot continue? For God will but onely blow vpon wealth, and it will melte. <hi>Riches make themſelues wings like an Eagle, and flie away:</hi> And therefore Chriſt ſpeaking of <hi>Diues,</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Erat,</hi> There was a certaine rich man. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayeth, Hee ſaw him ſpread and flouriſh like a green Bay-tree: Well? what became of him: I paſſed by his place, <hi>Et non erat,</hi> and hee was not. He was (ſayth our Sauiour) and is not. I ſaw him (ſayeth <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>) and hee was not. <hi>Ecce,</hi> Behold,
<hi>Erat, &amp; non erat, He was, and he was not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, for a full proofe of this, wee may compaſſe our ſelues with a whole cloud of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Tullie, Nihil tam anguſti, tamque parui animi, quam <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14978:11"/>amare pecuniam:</hi> Nothing argues ſo poore and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a mind as the loue of money. The Rich man in
<hi>Horace</hi> confeſſeth it; <hi>Populus me ſibilat,</hi> The people mocke at mee for a foole; And <hi>Solomon</hi> implyes it: where he ſayth:
<hi>Trauell not too much to bee rich, but
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe from that wiſedome:</hi> J, for that is a ſenſeles wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, no better then folly. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.5. They that will bee rich (ſayeth S. <hi>Paul</hi>) fall into many fooliſh and noyſome luſts, and in the caſe of wrangling and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to law hee asketh them. <hi>Is there not a wiſe man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> But the Prophet
<hi>Ieremy</hi> more plainely. As the Partridge gathers the young which ſhe hath not br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: So hee that gets riches, and not by right, ſhall leaue them in the middeſt of his dayes;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd at his end ſhall be a foole, <hi>Iam</hi> 17.11. <hi>Nabals his name, a Churle &amp; a Fool<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1 Sam. 25.23. and as though
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were ſome Bable-foole:
<hi>Iob</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Euery man ſhall
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appe their hands and hiſſe at him out of their place.</hi> Iob.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.22. And as he liues and dyes like a Foole; ſo hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be buried like an Aſſe, euen <hi>drawne and eaſt out, bidem, ver.</hi> 19. And therfore let euery wiſe man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent himſelfe with King
<hi>Solomon</hi> heere, to ſee this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill, not to feele it, to ſee it, and but to ſee it; to ſee it in others, not to know it in themſelues.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the proofe or euidence is from the place;
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Sunne.</hi> From whence we obſerue the Generality of this Sin. T'is <hi>MORBVS EPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEMICVS,</hi> euery where vnder the Sun: a diſeaſe and a plague infecting the whole world; or at leaſt, <hi>Maxima pars hominum, morbo iactatur eadem:</hi> poſſeſſing the greater number. The Prophet ſaieth all, <hi>From the greateſt to the least of them:</hi> Euery one is giuen to coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>touſneſſe; <hi>And from the Prophet to the Prieſt, they all deale falſly.</hi> Ierem. 6.13. And therefore the Wiſe man ſaith If any rich man eſcape it, hee is a bleſſed man, and works wonders in the world: for indeed this ſicknes ſeizes all. All men haue confeſſed themſelues <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14978:11"/>Bondmen thereto: In Court of <hi>Record,</hi> Princes, as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Achab:</hi> Prophets, as <hi>Balaam:</hi> Iudges and Rulers, as <hi>Foelix:</hi> Scribes and Phariſees, young men, women, and ſhepheards. Such a generall Pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique fellow is the couetous man, that hee is for all Companies. He will ſometime bee at Court, but not much. In the Citie he is all one with an Vſurer, or Broker; an Extortioner is his right hand. Nay, in theſe very aſtemblies; hee will ſometime bee of the great Inqueſt: ſometimes a Plaintiffe pleading <hi>in forma pauperis:</hi> and which I maruell at, hee is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent with all ſorts of ſchollers: and with Lawyers in drawing Conveiances, not a quirke eſcapes him: A r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re Phyſitian, hee will let blood ſtrangely: ô hee will plucke and ſucke like an Horſe-leach: and hee is very well ſeene in rootes: for hee hath the root of all rootes, <hi>Radicem omnium malorum, Of all Naladies, a true Paracelſian:</hi> All in his <hi>Alchymie,</hi> &amp; extraction, deals with nothing but Minerals, &amp; <hi>auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potabile,</hi> and is as faire for the Philoſophers ſtone, as the beſt of them. He is a very fierce
<hi>Sophiſter</hi> &amp; <hi>Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian;</hi> wreſting the premiſes any way: ſo he may bring or wring in his concluſion, regardles of either Mood or Figure: and a Muſitian, but he neyther obſerues time nor reſt, full of ſtops and frets, and idle crotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets; &amp; in ſome moods a Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marian: Marry, he is moſt in the <hi>Optatiue moode:</hi> his ſigne is
<hi>vtinam:</hi> and <hi>ô ſi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus ille proximus accedat qui nunc denormat agellum!</hi> wiſhing euer for new purchaſes; or if he grow ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall in the world that hee can paſſe to the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiue;</hi> that he fall once to ioyne houſe to houſe, and land to land: then hee neuer leaues till he fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Infinitiue:</hi> And yet wee doe not heare all; yet wee doe not heare the worſt of him: for as before we heard it proued: that this ſinne makes him a Murderer, a Lyar, and a Theefe: ſo it is a way to make him alſo a Coniurer, drawing the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14978:12"/>and all within his Circle; It makes him a Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; a Cheater, a Coyner, a Clipper, a Waſher, and laſt of all, a very <hi>Impe</hi> and
<hi>Zame</hi> of the Diuell. For as he can turne himſelfe into an Angell of light, ſo this his <hi>puney</hi> can lurke and skulke vnder a light Angell; ſometimes we may finde him in a crackt Crowne, or a braſſe ſhilling: So that as hee is euery where, ſo he does miſchiefe in all places. Thus you ſee manie maine Inditements againſt him; and therfore looke to him Iaylour, look to him <hi>Iurie;</hi> Be wiſe now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and learned, ò you
<hi>Iudges</hi> of the earth, that this generall <hi>Malefactor</hi> may receyue condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If hee be found guiltie but in ſome of theſe matters; you may touch him; but if in the greateſt hee be guiltie: of bloud, theft, violence, graſſation, and oppreſſion of the Poore; you may touch him, and twitch him too: Truſt him no longer, for it is full time he were truſſed.</p>
            <p>Againe, in this euidence of the place, we haue to obſerue the oppoſition to that place aboue the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: I haue ſeen't (ſayes
<hi>Solomon</hi>) vnder the Sunne. For ther's no ſuch thing aboue the Sunne. Theres a God aboue: a bountifull <hi>GOD,</hi> gratious, and liberall, Rich in grace, abundant and plentifull in mercie. Nay! the Creatures themſelues, the ſtarres of heauen are no Nigards, diſpenſing daylie their light and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to th'inferiour worlde. The <hi>Sunne,</hi> the right
<hi>Embleme</hi> of Liberality, continually ſhooting forth his glorious beames of Light. Nay: yet lower, the <hi>Moone,</hi> and th'inferiour Planets are not couetous: The three ſuperiour <hi>Elements</hi> are all free from this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: For that <hi>Tralucent Fire</hi> aboue vs is no deuourer like ours, fowle and foetulent heere below. And if Rich men were ſo good to theyr emptie Bretheren, (ſaith one) as the Ayre and water are to other empty things, as there is no voyde place in the World, So there would be no emptie perſon in the world. T'is <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14978:12"/>then thus lowe vnder the
<hi>Sunne,</hi> that it reſts onely in the dull and <hi>Foggie Element of Earth:</hi> for that indeed is Couetous, neuer ſayes <hi>Hoe:</hi> neuer ſayes, It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: So then t'is the earthly and muddie minde, which is infected with this ſicknes; This diſeaſe is onely the <hi>Churls Sickenes,</hi> no ſprightly nature: no vertuous or actiue diſpoſition is ſubiect therevnto. And giue me leaue (I beſeech you, right honourable and Chriſtian Auditors) to follow this <hi>Allegorie</hi> yet a little; becauſe in it, by way of application, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſhut and winde vp this diſcourſe. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Sunne;</hi> (The <hi>Sunne</hi> ſaith
<hi>Macrobius</hi>) is the King of <hi>Starres:</hi> So wee may iuſtly ſay of our moſt gracious King and Soueraigne, that hee is the <hi>Sunne</hi> amongſt men. Now then yet it holdes good that this diſeaſe is vnder the
<hi>Sunne:</hi> For though Couetouſnes hath bene prou'd to be <hi>Principium malorum,</hi> yet t'is not (God bee thank't) <hi>malum principis:</hi> Though it bee captaine and king of euills, yet hee's free from it, t'is vnder the
<hi>Sunne:</hi> Next vnder him, and thoſe Noble Staires of honour fix't aboue is your place (right <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi>) who like thoſe Planetarie bodies doe moue and <hi>Circuite</hi> about, for the preſeruation and good of the whole. O let not, let not this vile and wicked Infection ſticke in you, as it is vnder our gracious King the <hi>Sunne,</hi> ſo let it ſtill deſcend farre beneath your Throne of Iuſtice: Bee not like thoſe wicked
<hi>Iudges</hi> which <hi>Sophonie</hi> ſpeakes of, like Wolues in the Euening, that leaue no boanes vntill the Morning: nor like to <hi>Samuels</hi> ſonnes, which turned after <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre,</hi> and took reward, and peruerted iudgement: nor like to <hi>Falix,</hi> who lock't to receiue ſome thing of
<hi>Paule,</hi> but ſuch rather as <hi>Moyſes</hi> elected by
<hi>Iethroes</hi> counſell. <hi>Prouide thou among all the people Men of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, fearing God, men dealing truely and hating Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and appoint ſuch ouer them as rulers. Exod.</hi> 18.21. Such indeede are fitte to rule: For a couetous Iudge <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14978:13"/>is but a blind guide: For a reward puts out his eyes: it blindes the wiſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.17. Nay, it is a thing cleane oppoſite and contrary to Iuſtice; as it ſhould ſeeme by Saint <hi>Paules</hi> ſpeech; who, when he had warned <hi>Tymothy</hi> to flie from Couetouſneſſe, addes preſently, and follow Iuſtice. Remember that you are here placed in Gods ſtead; nay, <hi>Ipſe Dixi.</hi> I haue ſayde yee are Gods. God changes names with you: for as hee is called a iudge by <hi>Abraham;</hi> ſo a Iudge is ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led a God by <hi>Dauid.</hi> Bee then in this like God; This euill ſicknes is not in him: no, it is <hi>Malum Infirmum,</hi> an euill of infirmity, of infirme, weake and miſerable men. Thinke vpon this high and godlike function; thinke that the inferior <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are in your hands, to frame their conſciences; to ſtirre them to action: And therefore in the name of the Lord take heed, and beware of Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. O men of God flie theſe things, and follow Iuſtice, &amp;c. Let no cunning ſhift make offendors ſlide through your fingers; grow not dim n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or thicke ſighted with olde <hi>Iſaacke,</hi> leſt you like him bee deceiued in the feeling of <hi>Iaacobs</hi> hands. And the better to enforce this duety: Learne (Right Reuerend in the Lord, to auoyde the reſpect of perſons. For obſerue what <hi>Solomon</hi> hath in <hi>Prouer.</hi> 28.21. <hi>To haue reſpect of perſons in iudgement, is not good.</hi> Why? <hi>For ſuch a man will doe euill, euen for a peece of bread:</hi> See a reſpecter of perſons falles preſently into this euill diſeaſe, this raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and dogged appetite; that hee will ſnap at a Cruſt, do euill euen for a peece of bread. Shunne then wickedneſſe; for it is not good to haue any reſpect of perſons in iudgement: Hee thus ſayeth to the wicked, thou art righteous; him ſhall the people curſe, and the multitude ſhall abhorre him, and follow Iuſtice: For hee that walkes in Iuſtice, and ſpeakes righteous things refuſing <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14978:13"/>gaine of oppreſſion, ſhaking his hands from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of gifts, ſtopping his eares from hearing of blood, and ſhutting his eyes from ſeeing of euill, he ſhall dwell on high; his defence ſhall bee the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of rocks, bread ſhal be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; his waters ſhal be ſure. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.15.16. Giue not the people cauſe to take vp the complaint of the Prophet; <hi>Iudgement is turned backeward, and Iuſtice ſtands farre off, Trueth is fallen in the ſtreetes, and equitie cannot enter:</hi> but rather affoorde them cauſe to ſay with <hi>Solomon: I haue ſeene vnder the Sunne,</hi> the place of iudgement, where was iniquity, and the place of Iuſtice? where was wickedneſſe? And that this contagion may yet deſcend lower. Let not the Iuſtices and Gentlemen ſuffer themſelues to be tainted: Let not them fall into a violent graſſation, and grinding of the poore, racking and cramping, and ſqueeſing their poore te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, like the cruell <hi>Nero, Hoe agamus, ne quis quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam habeat:</hi> Let vs looke to this one thing, that no man haue any thing, falling vpon the poore like a tempeſt or a whirlewinde, leauing nought behind it. And you the ſage and prudent Lawyers, beware of this ſickeneſſe, take heed of tipping your tongue with ſiluer, or rowling it in golden eloquence.</p>
            <p>You are ſtiled by one of Gods own names, Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellour: Learne then to reſemble him in Nature, ſcorning this baſe and earthly diſeaſe of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>As for D uines, I hope well, the moſt part are free from this ſickeneſſe, becauſe it is a foule ſhame for the ſoules phyſition to lye ſicke of this vnſeemely diſeaſ.</p>
            <p>One word to the Iurors. Let nothing (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) friendſhip, or fauour; eſpecially, let not couetouſneſſe hinder your conſcience in right verdicts: neyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r bee too couetous of your Lords or Landlord
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>untenance, making him <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14978:14"/>as that common, yet fearefull ſaying is) to damne a dozen; but with courage and cleare ſoule proceed in iudgement.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, let euery couetous man, of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate or condition ſoeuer, that yet remaynes, obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and hardned in this ſinne of couetouſneſſe, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with this <hi>Caco-daemon,</hi> this euill ſpirite, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by hearty prayer and repentance, in time to eſcape from the griping fangs and clawes thereof; remembring that great and generall Aſsiſes, when wee ſhall all appeare (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunall ſeate of Chriſt, to receyue our doome; whoſe iudgement no writ of error can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, nor any attaint vndoe his verdict. At which time all cruell and couetous oppreſſors ſhall ſtand enuironed with thoſe poore Orphans and Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, whom they vniuſtly rooted out, and ſolde for ſhooes, now riſing vp to accuſe them: the iudge of heauen and earth; the Lord chiefe Iuſtice of all the world ouer them: hell gaping vnder them, when all their Pettyfoggers, that now ſwarme, will get them out of fight; when no Councellor or Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate will dare to open his mouth and plead for them: though they would giue him double and treble fees, when his owne conſcience ſhall bee a thouſand clamouro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s witneſſes to depoſe againſt him. In what a fearefull eſtate will this man bee then, who now goes on boldly, committing dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this wickedneſſe in the face of heauen, and vnder the Sunne? Surely, hee ſhall then wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnder the earth, and cry to the mountaines to fall downe and couer him. I dare not longer preſume vpon your patience: onely if this which I haue already ſpoken ſeeme tedious, I may in in ſome ſort, pleade excuſe from the nature of this euill ſickeneſſe, whereof I haue diſcourſed; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinite in it ſelfe, and without end, hath drawn
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14978:14"/>mee likewiſe to bee a little couetous of the time, and ſuffered mee no ſooner to make an end. <hi>To Ged Almighty, onely wiſe, the bleſſed Father, Sonne and holy Spirite, bee all prayſe and glory both now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Gloria Deo in excelſit.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14978:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
